																						
\j >;;/																						
R																						
"General Information,"																						
"General Data, Engine tuning Data,"																						
"Capacities, Fluid and Lubricants"																						
Maintenance																						
ROV E																						
S E  R  V  I  C  E                             Engine																						
Carburetter & Ignition																						
MEMS - SPi																						
Fuel Delivery System																						
MINI																						
Cooling																						
REPAIR MANUAL        Manifold & Exhaust																						
This Repair Manual covers all Mini models																						
"manufactured from VIN 049349, and should be used in conjunction with the following manuals:"																						
AKM 6845 - Mechanical Fault Finding Manual																						
Clutch																						
Manual Gearbox Automatic Gearbox Drive Shafts Differential																						
AKM 7181 - Body Repair Manual                                    Steering																						
Suspension																						
Brakes																						
Body																						
Heating & Ventilation																						
"f ,} A /C"																						
Publication Part No. AKM 7169																						
OROVER GROUP LIMITED 1993																						
Wipers and Washers																						
Electrical																						
Instruments




																						
INTRODUCTION																						
INTRODUCTION																						
How to use this manual																						
To assist in the use of this manual the section title is given at the top and the relevant sub - section is given at the bottom each page.																						
"Each section starts with a contents page, listing the information contained within. Some sections are divided into sub - sections such as Description and Operation, Adjustments, and Repairs. To assist filing of revised information each of the sub- sections is numbered from page 1."																						
The Adjustments and Repairs sub - sections are illustrated. The individual items comprising repair operations are to be followed in the sequence in which they appear. Items numbers in the illustration are referred to in the text.																						
"Adjustment and Repair operations include reference to Service Tool numbers and the associated illustration depicts the tool. Where usage is not obvious the tool is shown in use. Adjustment and Repair operations also include reference to wear limits, relevant data, torque figures, and specialist information and useful assembly details. In the majority of cases, each Adjustment or Repair operation is given its Repair Operation Time number for reference,"																						
"WARNINGS, CAUTIONS and Notes have the following meanings:"																						
WARNING: Procedures which must be to/lowed precisely to avoid the possibility of injury.																						
CAUTION: Calls attention to procedures which must be followed to avoid damage to components.																						
Note: Gives helpful information.																						
'References																						
'=leferences to the L.H.or R.H. side given in this nanual are made when viewing the vehicle from																						
Dimensions																						
The dimensions quoted are to design engineering specification with Service limits where applicable.																						
"During the period of running - in from new, certain adjustments may vary from 'the specification"																						
"figures given in this manual. These will be reset by the Dealer at the After Sales Service, and thereafter should be maintained at the figures specified in this manual."																						
REPAIRS AND REPLACEMENTS																						
When replacement parts are required it is essential that only Rover recommended parts are used.																						
Attention is particularly drawn to the following points concerning repairs and the fitting of replacement parts and accessories.																						
"Safety features and corrosion prevention treatments embodied in the car may be impaired if other than Rover recommended parts are fitted. In certain territories, legislation prohibits the fitting of parts not to the manufacturer's specification."																						
"Torque wrench setting figures given in this Manual must be used. Locking devices, where specified, must be fitted. If the efficiency of a locking device is impaired during removal it must be renewed."																						
Owners purchasing accessories while travelling abroad should ensure that the accessory and its fitted location on the car conform to legal requirements.																						
The Terms of the vehicle Warranty may be invalidated by the fitting of other than Rover recommended parts.																						
All Rover recommended parts have the full backing of the vehicle Warranty.																						
Rover Dealers are obliged to supply only Rover recommended parts.																						
'le rear. Wrth the engine and gearbox assembly                                                                                                     																						
"·<?moved, the crankshaft pulley end of the engine"																						
referred to as the front.																						
.. rations covered in this manual do not include rence to testing the vehicle after repair. It is ential that work is inspected and tested after																						
",pletion and if necessary a road test of the"																						
·icle is carried out particularly where safety																						
:ited items are concerned.																						
SPECIFICATION																						
"Rover are constantly seeking to improve the specification, design and production of their vehicles and alterations take place accordingly. While every effort has been made to ensure the accuracy of this Manual, it should not be regarded as an infallible guide to current specifications of any particular vehicle."																						
This Manual does not constiMe an offer for sale of any particular vehicle. Rover Dealers are not agents of Rover and have no authority to bind the manufacturer by any expressed or implied undertaking or representation.																						
I  I NTRODUCTION                                                                                                                                  																						
_INTRODUCTION																						
ABBREVIATIONS AND SYMBOLS																						
After Bottom Dead Centre After Top Dead Centre							A.B.D.C. A.T.D.C.	"Metre
Miles per hour"							m mph							
Air conditioning							AIC	Millimetre							mm							
Air fuel ratio							A.F.R.	Minimum							min							
Alternating current							ac	Minus (of tolerance)														
Amperes							A	Minute (angle)														
Anti - lock brake system (Bosch)							ABS	Model Year							MY							
Anti - lock brake system (Honda)							ALB	Modular engine management system							MEMS							
Before Bottom Dead Centre                B.B.D.C.              Multi - point injection                                MPi																						
Before Top Dead Centre                       B.T.D.C.                Negative (electrical)                                     ( -)																						
Bottom Dead Centre                                  B.D.C.                 Newton metre                                                 Nm																						
British Standards                                               B.S.                  Number                                                                No.																						
Carbon monoxide                                            co    Outside diameter                                         o.dia.																						
Celcius (Centigrade)                                           c																						
Centimetre                                                       cm																						
Percentage                                                       %																						
Compact Disc                                                C.D.                 Plus or minus                                                     ±																						
Cubic centimetres                                           cm3                          Plus (tolerance)                                                  +																						
Cubic inches                                                  in3                         Positive (electrical)                                          +																						
Cycles per minute                                        c/min                 Positive crankcase ventilation Positive temperature coefficient																						
PCV																						
PTC																						
Degree (angle)                                     deg. or 0                               Pounds mass                                                 lb																						
Degree (temperature)                         deg. or 0																						
Dial test indicator                                          DTI																						
Diameter                                                          dia.																						
Direct current                                                    de																						
Radius                                                                 r																						
Ratio																						
Reference                                                       ref.																						
Revolutions per minute																						
rev/min																						
Electronic Control Unit                                   ECU                 Right -hand                                                      RH																						
Exhaust gas reciriculation                     EGR            Right - hand drive																						
Electronic air control valve                         EACV                 Rover Engineering Standards																						
Fahrenheit                                                          F                 Second (angle)																						
Foot                                                                    ft                 Second (numerical order)																						
RHO																						
RES																						
2nd																						
Fifth                                                                  5th                 Single carburetter                                             SC																						
First                                                               1st                Single point injection                                     SPi																						
Fourth                                                              4th                 Specific gravity																						
Frequency Modulation                                     FM                 Square centimetres																						
Sp.gr																						
cm2																						
Gallons (Imperial)                                             gal                 Square inches                                                  in2																						
Gramme (mass)                                                  g																						
Standard                                                             std.																						
Synchronizer/synchromesh																						
synchro																						
High compression                                             he                 Third                                                                3rd																						
High tension (electrical)                                     ht                 Thousand                                                            k																						
Hour                                                                    h                 Top dead centre																						
TDC																						
Inches                                                             in                United Kingdom                                             UK Internal diameter                                         i.dia.																						
International Organization for                          ISO                 United States																						
Standardization                                                                       Vehicle identification number                          VIN Kilometre                                                          km                 Volt                                                                    v																						
Kilogramme                                                           kg                  Watt                                                                       w																						
Kilohertz                                                          kHz																						
Left -hand                                                      LH																						
Left - hand drive                                       LHD																						
Light emitting diode                               L.E.D. Litre                                                                I																						
Low Compression                                               le																						
Low tension                                                         It																						
Maximum                                                       max.																						
Mercury                                                            Hg																						
INTRODUCTION     I   3																						
INTRODUCTION																						
4       INTRODUCTION																						
GENERAL  INFORMATION																						
CONTENTS																						
Identification Numbers                                                             Page																						
Identification  numbers  .......................................................................................•2																						
Vehicle identification number plate                                                                   2																						
Engine number                                                                                                     2																						
Body number ............•.                                                                 2																						
General Precautions and Fitting Instructions                       Page																						
General precautions .•...•.                                                                                3																						
Ignition system safety precautions                                                                        3																						
Dangerous substances ··································-                             3																						
Engine oils ....................................•....•.                                             3																						
Health protection precautions •.....•..•...•...........................•.                         3																						
Environmental protection precautions ...........•.                                    3																						
Safety instructions                                                                                                3																						
Jacking ................................•.......•..•....••.                                             3																						
Precautions against damage                                                                                3																						
Brake   shoes   and   pads   .....•..•..•..•..........................•...•...•...•...••...•..•..•.....•..•.....•...4																						
Brake hydraulics ...•..........................................•.                                  4																						
Engine coolant caps and plugs ................................•..........•.....•.               4																						
Cleaning components                                                                                           4																						
Joints and joint faces .................................•................................................•.     4																						
Screw   threads     .........................•....•.........•....................................•.................•...4																						
Bolt identification ..........................•.                                           4																						
Nut identification  .........•...........•.............••.........................•.................•..........•.    5																						
Locking devices ............................•.................................................•.              5																						
Oil seals  .................•..............................................................................•.          6																						
Service tools and garage equipment                                                                    6																						
Body repairs ............................................................................................•.        6																						
Replacement body panels  .......•...•........••........................................•.......•.......•..6																						
Synthetic   rubber    .....•.....................•...•.................•••......................................•.•...6																						
Fuel Handling Precautions                                                     Page																						
Fuel handling precautions .............................•...........•.......................•.           7																						
General •......••...............••............•.•.                                                          7																						
Petrol - gasoline .......................•••..•..•.                                              7																						
Fuel tank   draining  ......•..••............•.•...•...............................................................•7																						
Fuel tank removal .......•.............•............•......................................•.               7																						
Fuel tank repairs .......................•...•................••.                                    7																						
Body and chassis repairs .....••....•.............................................•...................•.    7																						
Electrical Precautions                                                             Page																						
Electrical precautions ...................................................................•.......•..•.       8																						
Battery disconnecting ..............•.•.•.........•.............................•.                    8																						
Battery charging •.......................•......................•......••.....••.....................•.         8																						
Disciplines      ........•.......••.....................•..................................•...........................•..8																						
Grease for electrical connectors                                                                          8																						
GENERAL INFORMATION																						
IDENTIFICATION  NUMBERS																						
Vehicle identification number																						
"The Vehicle Identification Number (VIN) is stamped on a plate attached to the RH wing valance. As a deterrent to car thieves and to assist the police, the VIN is chemically etched on the windscreen and rear screen."																						
Vehicle identification number plate																						
S   A   X    XN   W  A    D   K   B   D   049349																						
Geographic are.a...          _.I   I																						
Country                                      ._																						
Manufacturer                                .																						
"Marque/Model,                         _."																						
Clas<>--------------'																						
BodY---------------'																						
Engine                                                                     .																						
Transmission and Steerin--------																						
"-""'"																						
111110S21c																						
Model change                                                           _.																						
"Assembly plan._                                                           ,"																						
Serial number                                                                            _.																						
Paint and Trim colour codes																						
3 - letter codes identifying the original Paint and Trim colours are stamped on the VIN plate																						
Paint                                                c  0   a																						
Basic colour                                                    Marque identifier																						
Colour/Shade name																						
Trim                                               L   0  y																						
Basic colour                                                    Marque identifier																						
Colour/Shade name																						
Engine number																						
Stamped on the front face of the cylinder block adjacent to the alternator.																						
Body number:																						
The body number is stamped on a plate fixed to the bonnet lock																						
platform.																						
GENERAL  INFORMATION																						
GENERAL  PRECAUTIONS																						
AND FIITING INSTRUCTIONS																						
Ignition system safety precautions																						
"WARNING: Before commencing work on an ignition system, all high tension terminals, adapters and diagnostic equipment tor testing should be inspected to ensure that they are adequately insulated and shielded to prevent accidental personal contacts and minimise the risk of shock. Wearers of surgically implanted pacemaker devices should not be in close proximity to ignition circuits or diagnostic equipment."																						
Dangerous substances																						
"WARNING: Many liquids and other substances used in motor  vehicles are poisonous and should under no circumstances be consumed and should, as tar as possible, be kept from"																						
contact with the skin. These substances																						
"among others include acid, anti - freeze, asbestos, brake fluid, fuel, windscreen washer additives, lubricants, refrigerant and various adhesives."																						
Always read carefully the instructions printed on labels or stamped on components and obey them implicitly. Such instructions are included tor reasons of your health and personal safety. Never disregard them.																						
"Used engine oils: Prolonged exposure to used engine oils can cause serious skin disorders, avoid excessive skin contact and always adhere to the following recommendations:"																						
Engine oils																						
"Prolonged and repeated contact with mineral oil will result in the removal of natural fats from the skin, leading to dryness, irritation and dermatitis. In addition, used engine oil contains potentially harmful contaminants which may cause skin cancer. Adequate means of skin protection and washing facilities must be provided."																						
Health Protection Precautions																						
"• Avoid prolonged and repeated contact with oils, particularly used engine oils."																						
"•  Wear protective clothing, including impervious gloves where practicable."																						
•  Do not put oily rags in pockets.																						
"• Avoid contaminating clothes, particularly underpants, with oil."																						
• Overalls rriust be cleaned regularly. Discard heavily soiled clothing and oil impregnated footwear.																						
•  First aid treatment should be obtained immediately for open cuts and wounds.																						
"•   Use barrier creams, applying before each work period, to help the removal of oil from"																						
the skin.																						
•  Wash with soap and water to ensure all oil is removed (skin cleansers and nail brushes																						
will help). Preparations containing lanolin replace the natural skin oils which have been removed.																						
"•  Do not use petrol, kerosene, diesel fuel, gas oil, thinners or solvents for cleaning skin."																						
"•   If skin disorders develop, obtain medical advice without delay."																						
"•  Where practicable, degrease components prior to handling."																						
"•  Where there is a risk of eye contact, eye"																						
"protection should be worn, for example, chemical goggles or face shields; in addition an eye wash facility should be provided."																						
Environmental Protection Precautions																						
"It is illegal to pour used oil on to the ground, down sewers or drains, or into water courses."																						
Burning of used engine oil in small space heaters or boilers can be recommended only for units of																						
approved design. The heating system must meet the regulatory standards of HMIP for small burners of less than 0.4 MV. If in doubt check with the appropriate local authority and/or manufacturer of approved  appliance.																						
"Dispose of used oil and used filters through authorised waste disposal contractors to licensed waste disposal sites, or to the waste oil reclamation trade. if in doubt, contact the Local Authority for advice on disposal facilities."																						
SAFETY INSTRUCTIONS																						
Jacking																						
"The recommended jacking points are given in LIFTING AND TOWING, always ensure that any lifting apparatus has adequate load and safety capacity for the weight to be lifted. Ensure the vehicle is standing on level ground prior to lifting or jacking. Apply the handbrake and chock the wheels."																						
Never rely on a jack as the sole means of support when working beneath the vehicle. Use additional safety supports beneath the vehicle.																						
"Do not leave tools, lifting equipment, spilt oil, etc. around or on the work bench area."																						
Precautions against damage																						
Always fit wing and seat covers before commencing work. Avoid spilling brake fluid or battery acid on paintwork. Wash off with water immediately if this occurs.																						
GENERAL PRECAUTIONS AND FITIING INSTRUCTIONS          3																						
Disconnect the battery earth lead before starting																						
"work, see ELECTRICAL PRECAUTIONS."																						
/IJways use the recommended service tool or a satisfactory equivalent where specified.																						
Protect exposed bearing and sealing surfaces and screw threads from damage.																						
Brake shoes and pads																						
WARNING: Always fit the correct grade and specification of brake linings and renew brake pads and brake shoes in axle sets only.																						
Brake hydraulics																						
WARNING: It is imperative that the correct brake fittings are usecl ancl that threads of components are compatible.																						
/IJways use two spanners when slackening or tightening brake pipe or hose connections. Ensure that hoses run in a natural curve and are not kinked or twisted. Frt brake pipes securely in their retaining clips and ensure that the pipe run cannot contact a potential chafing point.																						
"Containers used for hydraulic fluid must be kept absolutely clean. Do not store hydraulic fluid in an unsealed container, it will absorb water and in this condition would be dangerous to use. Do not allow hydraulic fluid to be contaminated with mineral oil, or use a container which has previously contained mineral oil. Do not re - use fluid from the system."																						
/IJways use clean brake fluid or a recommended alternative to clean hydraulic components. Frt a blanking cap to an hydraulic union and a plug to its socket after removal to prevent the ingress of dirt. Absolute cleanliness must be observed with hydrauiic  components.																						
Engine coolant caps and plugs																						
Extreme. care is necessary when removing engine coolant caps and plugs when the engine is hot and especially if it is overheated. To avoid the possibility of scalding allow the engine to cool before attempting coolant cap or plug removal.																						
Cleaning components																						
/IJways use the recommended cleaning agent or equivalent.																						
Do not use degreasing equipment for components cntaining items which could be damaged by the use of this process. Whenever possible clean components and the area surrounding them before removal. /IJways observe scrupulous cleanliness when cleaning dismantled components.																						
Joints and joint faces																						
Fit joints dry unless otherwise specified in this Manual.																						
If gaskets and/or jointing compound is																						
recommended for use; remove all traces of old jointing material prior to reassembly. Do not use a tool which will damage the joint faces and smooth out any scratches or burrs on the joint faces using an oil stone. Do not allow dirt or jointing material																						
to enter any tapped holes.																						
"Prior to reassembly, blow through any pipes, channels or crevices with compressed air."																						
Screw threads																						
Both U.N.F and Metric threads to ISO standards are used.																						
"Damaged nuts, bolts and screws must always be discarded."																						
Cleaning up damaged threads with a die or tap impairs the strength and closeness of fit of the threads and is not recommended.																						
"Castellated nuts must not be slackened back to accept a split - pin, except in those recommended cases when this forms part of an adjustment."																						
Do not allow oilor grease to enter blind threaded holes. The hydraulic action on screwing in the bolt or stud could split the housing.																						
/IJways tighten a nut or bolt to the recommended torque figure. Damaged or corroded threads can affect the torque reading.																						
"To check or re -tighten a bolt or screw to a specified torque figure, first slacken a quarter of a tum, then retighten to the correct torque figure."																						
Bolt identification																						
An ISO metric bolt or screw made of steel and larger than 6 mm in diameter can be identified by either of the symbols ISO M or M embossed or indented on top of the head.																						
"In addition to marks to identify the manufacturer, the head is also marked with symbols to indicate the strength grade, e.g. 8.8; 10.9; 12.9; 14.9. As an alternative, some bolts and screws have the M and strength grade symbol on the flats of the hexagon."																						
Always fit new roll pins of an interference fit in the																						
hole.																						
Always fit new circlips of the correct size for the groove.																						
@@    1DM OOl3																						
Self -locking nuts																						
"Self - locking nuts, i.e. nylon insert or metal stiff nuts can be re- used providing resistance can be felt when the locking portion of the nut passes over the thread of the bolt or stud."																						
Nut identification																						
A nut with an ISO metric thread is marked on one face or on one of the flats of the hexagon with the strength grade symbol 8. 12.or 14. Some nuts with a strength grade 4. 5 or 6 are also marked and some have the metnc symbol M on the flat opposite the strength grade marking.																						
A clock face system is used as an alternative																						
Self -locking bolts and screws																						
10MODl1																						
method of indicating the strength grade. The																						
external chambers or a face of the nut is marked in a position relative to the appropriate hour mark on a clock face to indicate the strength grade.																						
"A dot is used to locate the 12 o'clock position and a dash to indicate the strength grade. If the grade is above 12, two dots identify the 12 o'clock position."																						
Locking devices																						
"Always release locking tabs and fit new locking washers, do not re -use locking tabs. Always use a backing spanner when slackening or tightening brake and fuel pipe unions."																						
Fitting a split pin																						
Always fit new split - pins of the correct size for the hole in the bolt or stud. Do not slacken back nut to enter split - pin.																						
"Self - locking bolts and screws, i.e. nylon patched"																						
or trilobular thread can be re - used providing resistance can be felt when the locking portion enters the female thread.																						
Nylon patched bolts and screws have a locking agent pre - applied to the threads. They are identified by the presence of a coloured section of thread which extends for up to 180° around the thread.																						
Trilobular i.e. Powerlok bolts have a special thread form which creates a slight interference in the tapped hole or threads of the nut into which it is screwed.																						
"DO NOT re- use self - locking fasteners in critical locations e.g. engine bearings. Always use the correct replacement self - locking nut, bolt or screw."																						
"DO NOT fit non self - locking fasteners in applications where a self - locking nut, bolt or screw is specified."																						
GENERAL PRECAUTIONS AND FITTING INSTRUCTIONS            5																						
																						
"Service tools and garage equipment Special service tools have been developed to facilitate removal, dismantling and assembly of
mechanical components in a cost effective and practical manner without causing damage. Some operations in this Repair Manual cannot be carried out without the aid of the relevant service tools.
RM2652                                                                       A range of 'MICROCHECK' programme cards have been developed to provide a means of fast effective diagnosis of faults on electronic systems
Encapsulated bolts and screws                                     currently fitted to ROVER vehicles.
Encapsulated bolts and screws have a                       It is essential that operators familiarise themselves micro - encapsulated locking agent pre - applied to         with the components of the system to be checked the thread. They are identified by the presence of              and the instructions for the relevant
a coloured section of thread which extends                      'MICROCHECK' programme card before completely around the thread - 360°. The locking             commencing diagnosis.
agent is released and activated by the assembly                Where specific garage equipment is required for process and is then chemically cured to provide                diagnosis and repair, reference will be made in the locking action.                                                              this manual to the Service Tools and Equipment
Unless a specific repair procedure states                          Programme where details of the equipment otherwise, encapsulated bolts may be re - used                recommended by Rover Service may be found. providing the threads are undamaged and the
following procedure is adopted.                                            Body repairs
Remove loose adhesive from the bolt and housing                 Any damage found, that would affect the corrosion threads, ensure threads are clean and free of oil                    resistance of the vehicle during the Warranty
and grease. App!y an approved adhesive.                              period must be rectified by an authorised Rover
Dealer to the standards, and by the methods,
Fit a new encapsulated bolt, or if not available a                 detailed in the Body Repair Manual. bolt of equivalent specification treated with an
approved adhesive.                                                                   Replacement body panels
Body panels are supplied coated in cathodic
Oil seals                                                                              electrocoat primer.
AJways renew oil seals which have been removed
from their working location either as an individual                Synthetic rubber
component or as part of an assembly.                               Many 'O' rings, seals, hoses, flexible pipes and Ensure the surface on which the new seal is to                  other similar items which appear to be natural
rue , er, are in fact, made of synthetic materials
run is free of burrs or scratches. Renew the                      c :d Fluoroelastomers. Under normal operating component if the original sealing surface cannot                 c    :itions this material is safe and does not
be completely restored.                                                            i;.     ent a health hazard. However, if the material
Protect the seal from any surface which could                       il:: ..;amaged by fire or excessive heating, it can cause damage over which it has to pass when                      break down and produce highly corrosive
being fitted. Use a protective sleeve or tape to                   Hydrofluoric acid which can cause serious bums
cover the relevant surface.                                                        C'1 contact with skin. If skin contact does occur:
Lubricate the sealing lips with a recommended               •  Remove any contaminated clothing lubricant before use to prevent damage in initial                      immediately.
use. On dual lipped seals, smear the area                         •  Irrigate effected area with a copious amount between the lips with grease.                                                      of cold water or limewater for 15 to 60
Use the recommended service tool to fit an oil                                minutes.
seal.                                                                                         •   Obtain medical assistance immediately
If the correct service tool is not available, use a              Should the material be in a burnt or over - heated
suitable tube approximately 0.4 mm smaller than                    condition handle only with seamless industrial the outside diameter of the seal.                                             gloves. Decontaminate and dispose of gloves
Press or drift the seal in to the depth of its                         immediately after use. housing, with the sealing lip facing the lubricant to
be retained if the housing is shouldered, or flush with the face of the housing where no shoulder is provided."																						
	GENERAL PRECAUTIONS AND FITIING INSTRUCTIONS																					
6																						
FUEL HANDLING PRECAUTIONS																						
General																						
The following information provides basic precautions which must be observed if petrol (gasoline) is to be handled safely. It also outlines other areas of risk which must not be ignored.																						
"This information is issued for basic guidance only, and if in doubt appropriate enquiries should be made of your local Fire Officer."																						
Petrol - Gasoline																						
Petrol/gasoline vapour is highly flammable and in confined spaces is also explosive and toxic.																						
When petrol/gasoline evaporates it produces 150 times its own volume in vapour which when diluted with air becomes a readily ignitable mixture. The vapour is heavier than air and will always fall to																						
"the lowest level. It can readily be distributed throughout a workshop by air currents; consequently, even a small spillage of petrol/ gasoline is potentially very dangerous."																						
"Always have a fire extinguisher containing FOAM, C02, GAS or POWDER close at hand when handling or draining fuel or when dismantling fuel systems and in other areas where fuel containers are stored."																						
Always disconnect the vehicle battery before carrying out dismantling or draining work on a fuel system.																						
"Whenever petrol/gasoline is being handled, drained or stored or when fuel systems are being dismantled, all forms of ignition must be extinguished or removed; any leadlamps must be flameproof and kept clear of spillage."																						
WARNING: No one should be permitted to repair components associated with petrol/gasoline  without first having specialist training.																						
Fuel tank draining																						
WARNING: Petrol/gasoline must not be																						
extracted or drained from any vehicle whilst it is standing over a pit.																						
Draining or extraction of petrol/gasoline  from a vehicle fuel tank must be carried out in a well ventilated area.																						
The receptacle used to contain the petrol/gasoline  must be more than adequate for the full amount of fuel to be extracted or drained. The receptacle should be clearly																						
"marked with its contents,and placed in a sate storage area which meets the requirements of local authority regulations."																						
CAUTION: When petrol/gasoline has been extracted or drained from a fuel tank the precautions governing naked lights and ignition sources should be maintained.																						
Fuel tank removal																						
"When the fuel line is secured to the fuel tank outlet by a spring steel clip, the clip must be"																						
released before the fuel line is disconnected or the fuel tank is removed. This procedure will avoid the possibility of residual petrol fumes in the fuel tank being ignited when the clip is released.																						
As an added precaution fuel tanks should have a 'PETROL (GASOLINE) VAPOUR' warning label attached to them as soon as they are removed from the vehicle.																						
Fuel tank repairs																						
"Under no circumstances should a repair to any fuel tank involving heat treatment be carried out without first rendering the tank SAFE, by using one of the following methods:"																						
"a. STEAMING: With the filler cap and tank unit removed, empty the tank. Steam the tank for at least two hours with low pressure steam. Position the tank so that condensation can drain away freely, ensuring that any sediment and sludge not volatized by the steam is washed out during the steaming process."																						
"b. BOILING: With the filler cap and tank unit removed, empty the tank. Immerse the tank completely in boiling water containing an effective alkaline degreasing agent or a detergent, with the water filling and also surrounding the tank for at least two hours."																						
"After steaming or boiling, a signed and dated label to this effect should be attached to the tank."																						
Body and chassis repairs																						
"When a body or chassis repairs involve the use of heat, all fuel pipes which run in the vicinity of the repair area must be removed, and the tank outlet plugged, BEFORE HEAT IS APPLIED. If the repair is in the vicinity of the fuel tank, the tank must be removed."																						
"Plastic fuel pipes are particularly susceptible to heat, even at relatively low temperature, and can be melted by heat conducted from some distance away."																						
Fuel lines or tanks must not be removed whilst the vehicle is over an inspection pit.																						
FUEL HANDLING PRECAUTIONS            7																						
																						
"ELECTRICAL PRECAUTIONS                            Battery disconnecting
Before disconnecting the battery, switch off all
General                                                                           electrical equipment. If the radio is to be serviced, The following guidelines are intended to ensure                     ensure the security code has been deactivated. the safety of the operator whilst preventing                         CAUTION: To prevent damage to electrical damage to the electrical and electronic                               components ALWAYS disconnect the battery
components fitted to the vehicle. Where necessary when working on the vehicle electrical system. specific precautions are detailed in the relevant        The earth lead must be disconnected first and sections of this manual which should be referred                 reconnected last.
to prior to commencing repair operations.                          Always ensure that battery leads are routed Equipment - Prior to commencing any test                       correctly and are not close to any potential chafing procedure on the vehicle ensure that the relevant                 points.
test equipment is working correctly and any
harness or connectors are in good condition, this               Battery charging
particularly applies to mains lead and plugs.                                Recharge the. battery out of the vehicle and keep
WARNING: Before commencing work on an                  the top well ventilated. While being charged or ignition system all high tension terminals,                     discharged, and for approximately fifteen minutes adapters and diagnostic equipment for testing             afterwards, batteries emit hydrogen gas. This gas should be inspected to ensure that they are                  is inflammable.
adequately insulated and shielded to prevent               Always ensure any battery charging area is well
accidental personal contacts and minimise the             ventilated and that every precautions is taken to
risk of shock. Wearers of surgically implanted              avoid naked flames and sparks.
pacemaker devices should not be in close
proximity to ignition circuits or diagnostic                      Disciplines
equipment.                                                          Switch off ignition prior to making any connection Polarity - Never reverse connect the vehicle                or disconnection in the system as electrical surge
battery and always observe the correct polarity                      caused by disconnecting 'live' connections can
when connecting test equipment.                                          damage electronic components.
High Voltage Circuits - Whenever disconnecting             Ensure hands and work surfaces are clean and
live h.t. circuits always use insulated pliers and           tree of grease, swarf, etc. as grease collects dirt never allow the open end of the h.t. lead to come             which can cause tracking or high - resistance  . into contact with other components particularly                  contacts.
E.C.U's. Exercise caution when measuring the                  When handling printed circuit boards, treat them voltage on the coil terminals while the engine is                  as you would a hi-fi record - hold by the edges running, high voltage spikes can occur on these                only; note that some electronic components are terminals.                                                                           susceptible to body static.
Connectors and Harness - The engine                           Connectors should never be subjected to forced compartment of a vehicle is a particularly hostile                removalor refit, especially inter - board environment for electrical components and                      connectors, damaged contacts will cause short - connectors. Always ensure these items are dry                 circuit and open - circuit conditions.
and oil tree before disconnecting and connecting               Prior to commencing test, and periodically during test equipment. Never force connectors apart                    test, touch a good earth, i.e. cigar lighter socket, either by using tools or by pulling on the wiring                  to discharge body static as some electronic harness. Always ensure locking tabs are                          components are vulnerable to static electricity. disengaged before removal and not orientation to
enable correct reconnection. Ensure that any                        Grease for electrical connectors
protective covers and substances are replaced if                   All under bonnet and under body connectors are disturbed.                                                                                protected against corrosion by the application of a
Having confirmed a component to be faulty switch       special grease on production. Should connectors off the ignition and disconnect the battery.                    be disturbed in service or repaired or replaced, a Remove the component and support the                      grease of this type, available in 150 gm tubes disconnected harness. When replacing the                  under Part No. BAU 5811, should again be component keep oily hand away from electrical              applied.
connection areas and push connectors home until              Note: The use of other greases must be avoided
any locking tabs fully engage.                                                    as they can migrate into relays, switches etc. contaminating the contacts and leading to intermittent operation or failure."																						
8    I  ELECTRICAL PRECAUTIONS																						
INFORMATION																						
CONTENTS																						
General Data                                                                              Page																						
Engine ....................................................................................•.                           1																						
Fuel system - Carburetter ...................•...............................•...............•.        1																						
Fuel system  - SPi .........................................................•..................................1-																						
Cooling system                                                                                                      1																						
Clutch  .••....................................•...............•....................::...................•.•..•.               2																						
Manual gearbox   ..•..........................................................•..............................•.    2																						
Automatic gearbox .............................•........-.........•......•.                              2																						
Drive shafts  ........•..................•.•............•..................•......•...••.........•..•.....•.•.          2																						
Final  drive   .••.....................•..............•..•..........................................•............•••.       2																						
Steering         ..••............•............................•.......•...............•............................•........•.3																						
Suspension .......••••...........•....................••.•••..•......................................•..•.             3																						
Brakes .....••......•..•...................•...................................•..................•.                    4																						
Wheels   .••.........••............................•.....................................................•.•...••.         4																						
Tyres  ••••......•.......•••...............•..•..•.•..............•.......••......••..............••..•••.                     4																						
Electrical .•..•.••.•.••.......................•.••...........••.•......••.......•..•..................•.••.•.•.              5																						
"Dimensions  .......••...........•••...•.....•••••...•.•....••...•,...•..........•......................•••••...•.        5"																						
Weights       ...........••......•..•...•....•.•..•.•••....•.•...••..•..•.•.......••••.......•...•..........••....•......•.5																						
Engine Tuning Data                                                                  Page																						
1.3 Mini with Carburetter - Manual gearbox models .•••.•..•.............•..•.•.........•...1																						
1.3 Mini with Carburetter - Automatic gearbox models .•.....•........••••••...•.•.  2																						
1.3 Mini with SPi - Manual gearbox models .:.•..•••..••.•...............•••.••.....•.••.•...•..3																						
1.3 Mini with SPi - Automatic gearbox models ....•...................•.••..........•.•••.   4																						
1.3 Mini with SPi - High compression engine ••.........................•••.............•.  5																						
Torque Wrench Settings                                                          Page																						
General  •••.••••....••...•.......•..••.....•••••.................•.............................................•.               1																						
Maintenance      ....•............•....••..••.•••.........••....................................•......•........•..•...1																						
Engine •••........•••.••.....•..•....•.....••••..........•.••.....••...................................•.                    1																						
Carburetter  & ignition ••.•.......•...•.•.........•..•••.....•.•........••..••.•.............•••.....•.•••.       1																						
Modular engine management system - SPi •..........••.....•............•......•..•..•.•.  2																						
"Fuel     system      ....•.••••......••..••...•............•...•........•.....•...........•.••....•.......,.......•.......•.2"																						
Cooling .•.•.••.•...••...•.••...............••.......•.......•.•••••.••.....•...•..•..........••.....•.                 2																						
Manifold and exhausts  .•......•..........•.•..•••...•.•.........••.•.................•...••.....•.•.             2																						
Clutch     •..••..••..•...•.•..••.............•......................•••............•............•....••••.•.....•..••.•.•.2																						
Manual gearbox  •........•.••...••••..•.......•....•....................•........•................•.•.......•.     3																						
Automatic    gearbox     ....•...••.••......••••.....•...•.....••••.....••..........................••.•....••.•..•...3																						
Differential   ...••..•••••.....•....•.••.•..•.......••...••.........•.•..••..........................•.........••....•.3																						
Steering ••......••••••••.......••...•••..••......••.....••....••...•...•....•.............................••.•.         3																						
Suspension .....•.•.•................•...........................•..........•...................••.....••.             4																						
Brakes        .••••.........••.......•.....•.•••......•..........••................•....•.••.•...........•••.•.......•••.•...4																						
Body  ••••..........•••••....•..•....••.••••.•••..••........•..•..........•..•••••...••..........................•.           4																						
Electrical        ••..••..••.•••.•.•....••.•...•.•.....••................••..•..........................•..........•••....•...4																						
"Capacities, Fluids and Lubricants                                          Page"																						
Capacities  ..•••••••.•.......•.••...•.....•••....•.......••..•..•.....................•...••............•......•.            1																						
Fluids ••.•••....••.•••.•....•••••..••.•.••............................•...•.............•...•...............••..••.         1																						
Lubrication ..••...•.•.••••.•••....••.•...•......•.•...••••.•...................•••...•...........••....••.•.       2																						
INFORMATION																						
ENGINE																						
Engine number prefix  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Type . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .																						
Cylinder arrangement . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Bore . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .																						
Stroke . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .																						
Capacity  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .																						
Firing order  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .																						
Rotation . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .																						
Valve Timing																						
Inlet: Opens at . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .																						
Closes at . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .																						
Exhaust: Opens at  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .																						
Closes at . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .																						
Lubrication																						
System type																						
Relief valve opening pressure . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Pressure at idle . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Oil pressure warning light switch opens . . . .. . . Oil filter . . . . . . . . ... . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .																						
12A																						
8 valve																						
4 in line - transverse																						
70.61 mm																						
81.28 mm 1275 cm3																						
1 -3 - 4 -2																						
Clockwise																						
9° B.T.D.C.																						
41° A.B.D.C.																						
55° B.B.D.C.																						
17° A.T.D.C.																						
"Wet sump, camshaft driven eccentric rotor"																						
pump																						
4.2 kgf/cm2																						
1.05 kgf/cm2																						
0.4 to O.7 kgf/cm2																						
Full flow with renewable element cartridge																						
FUEL SYSTEM - CARBURETIER																						
Carburetter data . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . See Engine Tuning Data Fuel Pump																						
Type . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Mechanical camshaft driven																						
FUEL SYSTEM - SPi																						
Electronic fuel injection data . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . See Engine Tuning Data Fuel Pump																						
Type . . ... . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Electric immersible Pump maximum presure at 16V . . . . . . . . . . . . . 2.7 bar																						
Regulated injection pressure . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 1.0 to 1.1 bar																						
COOLING SYSTEM																						
Pressure cap opens . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 1.05 kgf/cm2																						
Thermostat open  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 88°C																						
Starts to open  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 85°C																						
Auxiliary cooling fan switch on temperature . . . . . . 98°C Switch off temperature  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 93°C																						
INFORMATION																						
CLUTCH																						
"Make and type . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . VertoNaleo, diaphragm spring. Hydraulically"																						
operated.																						
Clutch plate diameter  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 181 mm																						
Master cylinder bore . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 15.88 mm																						
Slave cylinder bore . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 22.22 mm																						
71/e in																						
0.625 in																						
0.875 in																						
MANUAL GEARBOX																						
Gear ratios:																						
Fourth                                                                     1.000:1																						
Third                                                                        1.425:1																						
Second                                                                       2.185: 1																						
First                                                                             3.647:1																						
Reverse                                                                      3.667:1																						
AUTOMATIC GEARBOX																						
"Type . . . . . . . . . . . .. . . . . . . • .. . . . . . . . .. .. Automotive Products, torque converter"																						
Gear ratios:																						
Drive .•                                                             1.0:1																						
Third                                                                     1.46:1																						
Second                                                                    1.845:1																						
First                                                                            2.69:1																						
Reverse                                                                      2.69:1																						
DRIVE SHAFTS																						
"Make and type . . . . .. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .. Hardy Spicer, solid shaft, with outboard"																						
constant velocity joints.																						
FINAL DRIVE																						
Gearbox code ECM 19/59 (Blue)																						
Ratio                                                                          3.105:1																						
Road speed at 1000 rev/min																						
Fourth . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .. . . . . . . . 28.6 kph																						
Third . . .. . . . . . .. . . . .. . . . .. . . .. . . . . . . . 20.1 kph																						
Second  . . . • . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 13.1 kph																						
First  . . . . . . . . ... . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 7.9 kph																						
17.8 mph.																						
12.5 mph																						
8.2 mph																						
4.9 mph																						
Speedometer gear ratio                                               7:17																						
2  I GENERAL DATA																						
Gearbox code HPD 19161 (Green)																						
Ratio                                                                              3.21:1																						
Road speed at 1000 rev/min																						
Fourth . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 29 kph																						
Third . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 20.3 kph																						
Second  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 13.3 kph																						
First  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 7.9 kph																						
18.0 mph																						
12.6 mph																						
8.2 mph																						
4.9 mph																						
Speedometer gear ratio                                               7:17																						
Automatic gearbox																						
Ratio                                                                             2.69:1																						
Road speed at 1000 rev/min																						
Drive . . .. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 29.3 kph																						
Third . . .. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 20.1 kph																						
Second . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .. . . . . . . . 15.9 kph																						
First  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 10.9 kph																						
18.2 mph																						
"12,5 mph"																						
9.9 mph																						
6.8 mph																						
Speedometer gear ratio                                               7:17																						
STEERING																						
Type . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Rack and pinion																						
Front wheel alignment . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 1f1s in Toe -out         1.6 mm																						
Front wheel camber  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 2° ± 1° Positive																						
Front wheel castor  . . . . . . . . . . . . . : . . . . . . . . . 3° ± 1° Positive																						
Steering angle of wheels at full lock . . . . . . . . . . . Inner wheel 34.5° . Outer wheel 30° Steering wheel turns - lock to lock                      2.7																						
Rear suspension geometry																						
Rear wheel camber   . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 1/s in Toe - in            3.18 mm																						
Rear wheel camber  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 1° positive + 1.5° -0.5°																						
Note: Steering and suspension geometry settings are for a vehicle at kerbside weight.																						
SUSPENSION																						
Front																						
Type                                                                             Independent rubber cone spring with																						
telescopic hydraulic dampers.																						
Rear																						
Type                                                                             Independent trailing arm with rubber cone																						
spring and telescopic hydraulic dampers.																						
Radius arm bushes (reamed bore) . . . . . . . . . . . . 0.8145 to 0.8150 in 20.69 to 20.70 mm																						
INFORMATION																						
BRAKES																						
Type  . . . . • . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .  Servo assisted Lockheed hydraulic; disc front																						
"with fixed calipers, drum rear with leading and trailing shoes and manual adjustment."																						
"Split line system, front to rear, with pressure reducing valve.                                        -"																						
Front brakes																						
Disc diameter . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 8.4 in																						
Pad minimum thickness   . . • . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 1/s in																						
213.4 mm																						
3 mm																						
Rear brakes																						
Brake drum:																						
Inside diameter   . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 6.75 in Lining minimum thickness  . . . . . . . . . . • . . . . . . •   1/s in																						
171.5 mm																						
3 mm																						
Servo type . • • . • . . . . . • . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Lockheed T28 DA																						
WHEELS																						
Size  . .. . . . • . • . . . . . . . . . . • . . . . . • • . • . . . . 41/2 B x 12 Steel																						
41/2 B x 12 Alloy 58 x  12 Alloy																						
TYRES																						
Size                                                                              145170 - SR12 658																						
165/60 - R12 71H																						
Pressures (cold):																						
Size					Loading Condition					bar	kg/cm2		lbflin2									
145170 SR12					All conditions				Front	2.0	2.0		28									
									Rear	2.0	2.0		28									
165160 R12					All conditions				Front	2.0	2.0		28									
									Rear	2.1	2.1		30									
4    I GENERAL DATA																						
ELECTRICAL																						
"System . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 12 Volt, Negative earth return with voltage"																						
control.																						
Battery																						
Type - Maintenance free                                    138																						
Cold crank . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 265 amps																						
Reserve capacity  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 45 minutes																						
Alternator																						
Type  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . A127 - 45																						
Maximum output . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 45 amps																						
Regulate . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 21TR																						
Staner motor																						
Type . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . M79																						
Power  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 0.8 kW																						
DIMENSIONS																						
Overall length																						
Saloon   . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ... . . ;• . . • . . . . . 3.05 m																						
Cabriolet  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.09 m																						
Overall width (including mirrors) . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 1.58 m Overall height																						
Saloon                                                                    1.34																						
Cabriolet  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 1.364 m																						
Ground clearance																						
Saloon   . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 163 mm																						
Cabriolet . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 102 mm																						
Wheelbase . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ... . . . . ... . . . . . 2.04 m																						
Turning circle (kerb to Kerb) .. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 8.6 m																						
10 ft 01/4 in																						
10 ft 2 in																						
5 ft 2t in																						
4 ft 43/4 in																						
4 ft 53/4 in																						
51/2 in 4 in																						
6 ft 81/4 in																						
28 ft 6 in																						
WEIGHTS																						
Unladen weight (full fuel tank without options)																						
1.3 Carburetter models																						
Manual . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ... . . . . . . . .																						
Automatic  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .																						
1.3 SPi models																						
Manual  . . . . ... . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .																						
Automatic  . . . . . ... . • . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .																						
1.3i Cooper . . ... . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .																						
Cabriolet  . . . . . . • . . . . . . • . ... . . . . . . . . . . .																						
Max gross vehicle weight																						
Saloon  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .																						
Cabriolet  . . • ... . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .																						
Maximum roof rack weight (distributed) . . . . . . . . . Maximum towing weight with braked trailer -																						
"restart 12%, 1 in 8 gradient with two occupants"																						
in vehicle . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .																						
685 kg																						
710 kg																						
685 kg																						
710 kg																						
695 kg																						
760 kg																						
1050 kg																						
1070 kg																						
40 kg																						
405 kg																						
1510 1b																						
1565 lb																						
1510 1b																						
1565 1b																						
1532 1b																						
1676 1b																						
2315 kg																						
2359 1b																						
90 lb 895 1b																						
Towing hitch downward load  . • . . . . . . . . . . . . . .																						
50 kg                        110 lb																						
